Rajani Raman, PhD

Summary

A neuroscientist with 10+ years of research experience in investigating the computational mechanism of the visual system using machine learning methods and artificial neural networks. A proven track record of publications, programming, problem-solving, and communication. A quick learning, self-motivated individual that can easily integrate into interdisciplinary collaborative work and work environment.

Research Experience

2020- Postdoctoral Researcher, KU Leuven, Leuven, Belgium

Present Investigating how does the brain process the visual information from the body-movements, using the tools of machine learning, fMRI, and electrophysiology in macaque (with Prof. Rufin Vogels and other collaborators in an ERC Synergy project)

2017 – 2020 Research Scientist, ATR Cognitive Mechanism Labs, Kyoto, Japan

Assessed different deep neural networks as a model of face processing against the observed tuning properties of neurons in the face patches of macaques (with Dr. Haruo Hosoya)

2011 - 2017 PhD Researcher, Saha Institute of Nuclear Physics, Kolkata, India

Investigated computational mechanism of the filling-in phenomenon at the blind spot and associated properties in the framework of predictive coding model of natural images (under supervision of Prof. Sandip Sarkar)

Research Interests

Visual recognition and perception | Predictive coding and Bayesian inference | Deep learning | Natural scene statistics

Skills

Technical: Machine and Deep learning | Data and Visual analytics | Coding in Matlab and Python

Soft: Problem solving | Adaptability | Critical thinking | Teamwork | Communication | Empathy

Publications

- Murris S, Arsenault J, Raman R, Vogels R, Vanduffel W. Electrical stimulation of the macaque ventral tegmental area drives category-selective learning without attention. *Neuron*, 2021.
- Raman R, Hosoya H. Convolutional neural networks explain tuning properties of anterior, but not middle, face-processing areas in macaque inferotemporal cortex. *Communications biology*, 2020.
- Raman R, Sarkar S. Significance of Natural Scene Statistics in Understanding the Anisotropies of Perceptual Filling-in at the Blind Spot. *Scientific Reports*, 2017.
- Raman R, Sarkar S. Predictive Coding: A Possible Explanation of Filling-In at the Blind Spot. PLOS ONE, 2016

Selected Conference Presentations

- M. Beghella Bartoli, *Raman R, N. Taubert, Y. Zafirova, B. De Gelder, M. Giese, R. Vogels. Mapping dynamic body patches in macaque inferotemporal cortex. SfN Annual Meeting, 2021 (online). *Presenting author
- Raman R, Hosoya H. Does CNN explain tuning properties of macaque face-processing system? CCN, 2019, Berlin, Germany.
- \circ Raman R, Hosoya H. Evaluating CNNs as a model of face processing network of the macaque, $42^{\rm nd}$ JNS Annual Meeting, 2019, Toki Messe, Japan. (talk)
- Raman R, Hosoya H. Does CNN explain the properties of the middle face patch area of primate? SfN Annual Meeting, 2018, San Diego, CA.
- Raman R, Sarkar S. Understanding Anisotropies Related to the Filling-In at the Blind Spot in the Light of Natural Image Statistics, JNNS-2017, Kitakyusyu, Japan.
- Raman R, Sarkar S. Studies on filling-in across blind spot in the light of hierarchical predictive coding of natural images, ICMCB 2015, IIT Kanpur, India. (talk)

Schools

- Summer School on Computational Approach to Memory and Plasticity, 2014, NCBS, Bangalore, India.
- Cold Spring Harbor Asia Summer School: Computational and Cognitive Neuroscience, 2013, Beijing, China.

Education

2011-2017 PhD, Saha Institute of Nuclear Physics, Kolkata, India

Thesis: Computational mechanism of filling-in in the visual system

2010-2011 Pre-doctoral training, Saha Institute of Nuclear Physics, Kolkata, India

Specialization: Computational vision and neuromorphic design

2007-2009 MSc (Physics), Patna University, Patna, India

Specialization: Electronics and Instrumentation

Scholarships

- Senior research fellowship, Department of Atomic Energy, Govt. of India (2013 2016).
- o Junior research fellowship, Department of Atomic Energy, Govt. of India (2010 2013).
- Madhava Maharupi Physics Scholarship at Patna University, India (2007 2009).

Professional Associations

Society for Neuroscience (SfN) \mid Federation of European Neuroscience Societies (FENS) \mid Vision Sciences Society (VSS) \mid The Japan Neuroscience Society (JNS)

Activities

Mentoring/collaborating with PhD and Master students | Science outreaches | Blood donation camps